What's up everyone? Skimmy here. I know a
lot of you have been after this video for
quite some time now, and we finally got
around to making it. So, this will be my
updated guide for Shadow Priest in Mop Classic.
For those of you that don't know me or have never
seen one of my videos, a little bit about
myself is that I've been making these since
WOTLK Classic. Really, I've been enjoying the
nostalgia of going down memory lane and at the
same time playing an underdog spec, right,
which tends to underperform or get negative
press compared to mages, warlocks, or whatever.
So, trying to change the narrative around that
shadow priest suck and that we always pay the
utility tax price. Whilst that can certainly
be true at times, we can definitely hang with
the best if we know what we're doing from a
class and fight perspective. Last week, I was
fortunate enough to get myself three rank ones
on the launch of Heart of Fear. Hopefully, by the
end of this guide, you'll have learned a thing or
two to help reach those numbers yourself as well.
Now going into MOP, one of the biggest changes was
the overhaul to the talent system. Gone are the
days of having 40 different talent points to play
around with, figure out, and basically never
change again. So that's all gone away. We've
now got six rows to tinker around with based on
the kind of content we're up to, be it dailies,
PvP, or raids like we have here, right? So, I've
added a cheat sheet as to what I take based on
the boss and we can discuss the logic as to why we
take what we do. So, with the first talent here,
it's not that impactful. You'll see, even
on Zorlok, I untalent it completely because
it's just one less way to grief for the raid if I
get mind controlled. It's a utility talent here,
right? So, doesn't really matter all too much.
I wouldn't stress this one whatsoever. You get
to your second row, you've got angelic feather.
This for me is the goat. It's non-negotiable.
It's really strong in this version of the
game. So, don't consider anything else in my
opinion because if you look at body and soul, you
might have played it in retail and thought, "Hey,
that's quite handy as a quality of life buff." My
problem with that, though, is that the shield, a
healing priest is going to be better for that, as
well as if you've got that debuff, you can't get
the movement speed when you really need it. Right.
So, Angel is the best pick for me, and we'll talk
about that a little bit more in a moment. With
the next tier, you can choose all three options.
Although, surprisingly or maybe unsurprisingly,
solicited insanity is the best option. It's the
biggest boost for our single target, which is what
shadow priest needs. But the likes of Mindbender
and from darkness comes light come with a fair bit
of value as well. For Stone Guard in particular,
I run Mindbender just because I get to stand
still. We get the hunters to do all the painting,
and you get to cleave all four dogs together.
Pop your Mindbender. You're never going to hit
mine flare because you're doing mines instead, and
you can focus on that. If you're doing a different
strategy, perhaps you're painting as well, then
from darkness comes light can be quite handy as
well, just because it gives you the ability
to cast something as you're running around,
which can sometimes feel a little bit awkward
for shadow priest, right? Because if you're not
in execute phase, what are you going to do? You're
going to be hitting shadow word pain resets. It's
nothing too fancy. With the next talent here,
Angela Bulwark for me is just another nice little
not a cheap death proc but certainly a substantial
HP buffer when you get low. I think to the days of
the final phase of Sinragoth, everybody's running
around having to LoS because their stacks are
getting too high, and you're just standing still
with vampiric embrace blasting. So, adds to that
makes you feel still fairly tanky, fairly durable.
The only time I would untalent this would be on
Amber-Shaper. I'd go for desperate prayer instead.
Reason being, if you become the construct,
the bulwark shield scales with the construct, and
you can suddenly get like a 2 million shield. So,
everyone will be laughing at you, and look, don't
be that guy. I've been there once. Once. Lastly,
or actually second to last, we've got the
argument between Power Infusion and Twist of Fate.
Unfortunately for me, Divine Insight is really
far behind. Can't really make an argument for it
this phase. Perhaps later on, unsure. These two
are just so incredibly strong. The argument for
me between these is if you can get at least 50%
uptime, then Twist of Fate's going to be better.
Otherwise, Power Infusion. The reason being is,
if you got plenty of different ads throughout the
fight that you can snipe, that shadow word death,
that's more shadow orbs, that's more flat bonus
damage from having that proc up all the time,
it's a really big deal. But if it's a flat single
target fight like Fang or Blade Lord, PI is going
to be a little bit nicer, and you can line those
up quite nicely to have one in the opener, one in
the execute phase or second pot, and really get
some good value there. Lastly, Halo is by far our
strongest level 90 talent. Obviously, the caveat
is you need to be a fair distance away from the
boss to make sure it ramps up its damage. There
are arguments to take Cascade, and those will
be for just Elegon and Golon at this point, and
divine star has its purpose, but in raiding, only
if you're ever forced to do a stack hard stack
strategy or in celestial dungeons when you're
farming, it's going to be the superior choice
there, but we'll talk about that a little bit
more in a second as well. So, the reason I like
this version of Angel so much compared to what
we have in retail is, well, first of all, just
comparing them side by side, you've got double
the movement speed. It lasts a second longer,
and then the cooldown time is halved. I mean, that
for me is a no-brainer. It's crazy how much we go
from being a wheelchair class that gets a mechanic
and goes, "Gee, boots are on cooldown. I can't
do anything now," to like, "Hey, 80% move speed
for 6 seconds." It's hard to not have it up and
available, I suppose, is what I'm getting at here,
right? Whereas you compare it to retail, you're
like, "Gee, no warlock gate or no evoker rescue
grip, whatever it may be. I can't deal with these
mechanics." And, yeah, it feels bad, man. I've
been there. I've been there when I played retail
recently. So, having this feather now in MOP
feels so good that you can be the speedy class,
and you can get to laugh at other people, right?
Like, obviously, Blade Lord in Heart of Fear where
everyone goes super zoom, I'm never lost.
Alright. So, hey, that's a massive improvement
over what we've had in previous expansions for
classic. In terms of the other talents as well,
so for level 90, as I mentioned before, we've got
Halo as our default. Now, the condition is, yeah,
at least 20 yards and above, and that's going to
always be a DPS boost. If you are forced to stack
in melee because that's the strategy on the boss,
or if you're just farming your celestial dungeons,
right, to get your character geared, Divine Star
is going to be far better. Divine Star is just
going to smooth it out and do more damage if
you're closer to that target. At this point,
yeah, Elegon and Golon would be the only arguments
for when you'd be taking Cascade. Otherwise, yeah,
just get comfortable with using Halo, having a
weak aura or an add-on or some way of tracking
your distance, and weaving that in terms of the
spell priority, which we'll cover shortly. Now,
like any class, there's obviously a stat priority,
which is beneficial or their best in slot,
right? But before you even consider that, I would
say that nine times out of 10, item level is the
overall winner just because you're getting so
much extra stamina, raw main stats, secondary,
sometimes socket bonuses. A combination of that
spread across so many different item slots,
that alone tends to just be flat-out better. But
obviously should never be at the expense of making
sure you're hitting these major points, which is
easier than ever now to do, right? So, in terms
of hit cap, you want to hit 15%. That's what that
blue line is on the graph below. After that point,
reforge, regem, re-enchant. Don't bother with
it anymore, just because you don't need it,
right? So, 15% easier than ever. As I said before,
you got hit rating. We convert spirit as a passive
into hit as well. Now, expertise counts for
casters as hit. So, 15% is the magic number
there. Right off that number one priority as
a dot-focused class is haste. 8085 is a number
you're going to be seeing a lot in the next
few slides. It's a major breakpoint in terms of
when our haste just gives us extra damage through
extra dot ticks. At this stage in phase one, crit
is just ever so slightly better than mastery. But
as we go later into the expansion with different
tier sets with different items available, that
relationship will ping-pong back and forward. To
help understand why haste is so important for us,
you first need to understand what it does for our
dots. So, you'll see here our three main dots
we'll be using in MOP Classic. They all have a
fixed duration, and within that time, they'll
be doing a set amount of damaging ticks. So,
the more haste you have, it's not only going to
reduce how long it takes to cast your spells,
it's going to reduce your global cooldown, make
the gameplay feel smoother, rotation feel nicer,
it's also going to add additional ticks within
that same amount of time. So, for instance,
Devouring Plague might do eight ticks of damage
instead of six within that same 6-second period.
Now, with the breakpoints, the first one is
super easy to achieve. You get 5% baseline
from your shadow form. The rest, quite honestly,
I'm sure anybody, even somebody in full boosty
boy green gear, is going to be able to hit this
first tick, no drama. The real kicker, the real
one you want to dial in on and focus in ahead as
quickly as possible, is 8085. That's two extra
ticks of shadow word pain. Conveniently enough,
it's two extra ticks of Devouring Plague as well.
That's the name of the game in this expansion: to
build and spend orbs and cast the spell as often
as you possibly can. Now, certainly with enough
raid gear, enough item level, 30% is going to be
achievable, and definitely later down the line
come Throne of Thunder as well as Siege, 14k,
18k, that'll be achievable as well. So, in terms
of late-game scaling, when you talk about the
argument of us, affliction warlocks, fire mages,
and so on, this is what they're referring to,
right? Certain benchmark areas that won't become
obtainable unless you have enough gear to make it
possible. But definitely, the relationship between
8085 and 10k, play around in the MOP sim. It's not
necessarily worth just giving pure haste to hit
it. You might not have to once you have access
to tier 14 four-piece because that's going to
increase the duration of both shadow word pain and
vampiric touch by 3 seconds. That's going to give
you an additional tick for free by default. It's
also going to change the haste breakpoints once
again. So, if you got a bit of a keen eye, you'll
note that vampiric touch looks like the formula
used for shadow word pain in the previous slide.
That means it's adopted those haste breakpoints,
and once again, 8085 becomes front and center,
the haste rating to work towards. So, depending
on your gearing situation, you're going to want
to gem match with quick suns and energized wild
jade very early on to try and hit that 8085 as
quickly as you can. Obviously, you got reforging,
you got enchants, and so on that make it a little
bit easier as well. But definitely, depending on
your situation, maybe you're a fresh level 90 or
just been really unlucky with raid loot, and
it's not dropped any haste gear, you're going
to want to use these to try and hit that point as
quickly as you can. But if you're playing around
in the MOP sim and if you're comfortable
with it and you're realizing that, hey,
it's no longer worth chasing the next breakpoint
afterwards, I'm sacrificing too much of intellect,
for example, then that's when you're going
to start to swap these out for the reckless
and purified gems instead. As the expansion goes
on, we've got a lot of stat scaling to play with,
right? So, comparing two weapons from phase 1 and
phase 5, you can see right off the bat, you've got
double the spell power, a ton, basically double
the stamina as well, a ton of raw intellect to
play with, a socket bonus, which is always a nice
addition, and same to be found on secondaries with
your rings, right? So, you've got again double
the health, a ton of intellect to play with,
and all that secondary nearly double again there,
too. So, your times just by 18 equivalent slots,
and you can quite clearly see just how powerful
it's going to be with the stat scaling. You'll
hit certain breakpoints. You'll be able to hit GCD
cap. Scaling classes like ourselves, fire mage,
and all the rest are going to have such a fun
time. That's when you're going to truly feel
like Thanos and feel rewarded for sticking it out
when you suck at the start, but by the end game
of an expansion, you're up there with the best,
right? So, now that we got ourselves all set with
housekeeping, we're running the right talents,
we got our gear in check, and our stats to match,
it's time to start playing the game. In terms of
a pre-pull ritual, what I like to do is stand at
least 28 yards away from the boss. Whilst
it's a little bit difficult nowadays with,
you know, we is they make you guesstimate between
25 and 30. If you stand at this distance because
Halo has a travel time, if you cast at 2 and a
half seconds on your pre-pull countdown timer,
then it's going to connect with that boss on
zero from that distance. Obviously, if you stand
closer, then adjust the timer accordingly. But
this just makes it do as much damage as possible
when you can control that distance, especially
in a pre-pull situation. A second before you go,
I hit my pop. Then I do mind spike instead of
vampiric touch just because I'm looking to try and
activate as many ways as possible to pop passive
trinkets to activate jade spirit weapon enchant
that when I eventually hit things like berserking
PI and engineering gloves, you've got so many
active buffs available that you're empowering that
first round of dots to be as strong as possible,
right? The idea of snapshotting, if you will. So,
once you got that first set of dots up and active,
before I go into that mind flay, instead of me
spamming, because you are always building orbs
and then spending them, you want to make sure
you're pressing mind blast on cooldown. So, you
hit that next and then go into mind flay insanity
spamming. Now, one really exciting part of MOP is
the change to shadow fiend. This can now actually
be cast after bloodlust, and it will still receive
that buff. Gone are the days of, "Hey, I've just
hit my shadow fiend, guys. Second last, please."
Doesn't matter anymore. It will dynamically update
after it's spawned. It's going to go up. Bloodlust
is active, and it's going to respond in that
fashion. So, it's a really nice quality of life
buff and smooths out the rotation compared to say
Dragon Soul or Trillium. You're like, "Guys, can I
get a lust?" And they're like, "Nah, it will grief
our healers, and you just, you know, feels bad,
man." Once we finished our opening, here's the
spell priority I like to follow, which, name of
the game, as I said before, it all revolves around
building and spending shadow orbs. Very different
to Cataclysm, where it was all RNG-based. Now
we have full control as to when we get them. So,
we want to make sure we have perfect uptime on
that. So, Devouring Plague, you only ever want
to cast this at three orbs. With mind blast, we
prioritize over mind flay and suddenly in the open
in execute phase. Shadow Word: Death obviously
gets added into the mix. Always use these spells
on cooldown and plan ahead because that really
is the name of the game. We are a juggling act
as shadow priest, right? Juggling multiple
plates at once to try and min-max our value,
and that's where the skill expression can
certainly come from. After this point, mind
flay insanity has perfect harmony with Devouring
Plague. You want to try and channel as many of
those as possible. Then, assuming you already have
your dots up and active, you'd want to make sure
you're refreshing them at this point. You know,
below got a little bit of a disclaimer about this,
right? So, the planning ahead aspect, you want to
make sure that both shadow word pain and vampiric
touch would have at least 8 seconds remaining
before you cast Devouring Plague. That way,
you just have the ability to chain those insanity
mind flays one after the other and do as much
damage as possible. So, by planning ahead,
you're not bottlenecking yourself. You're not
gimping your damage and trolling your output
to make us look worse than we are. Come on,
guys. We got to make Shadow Priest look strong.
After this point, from darkness comes light. Yeah,
if you're running this talent, this is when
you'd be using those procs. Really handy,
especially when you're on the move. Fills in that
dead space when you can't do mind flay or cast a
dot refresh. If you're able to stand at least 20
yards away, this is when you'd want to prioritize
things like Halo. Otherwise, mind flay regular
is your short filler spell. Does a fair bit of
damage. So, don't get too obsessed with ideas of
snapshotting. Regular mind flay still does pack a
bit of a punch. But if any of the above spells
were needing to be refreshed or used because
they've come off cooldown, obviously that's when
you would interrupt it. Now, the reason why mind
flay insanity is so highly prioritized is, well,
first of all, Devouring Plague buffs it by 33% for
each orb that's used. So, assuming we're only ever
using it with three orbs, each mind flay insanity
is doing 100% bonus damage, which is a pretty big
deal and a significant boost to our single target,
which is what is lacking at the moment. One
of the ways you can edge out even further
DPS gains is to recast mind flay insanity just
before Devouring Plague falls off, and it's going
to snapshot and retain that damage for the entire
channel. Which is a pretty big deal, right? So,
if you were to compare yourself once again to
another different shadow priest and say like,
"Oh, what are they doing?" You could compare
just how much damage their mind flay insanity
did compared to yours, linking it to how many
Devouring Plagues they cast. Look, you can go down
that rabbit hole if you want to min-max. You can
get a bit of insight as to like why are they doing
more? A lot of the time, this is going to come
down to understanding these mechanics and how to
play around that. I get a lot of comments from you
guys asking what weak auras and add-ons I'm using.
Each time I upload a video, in the description,
I include this link that you see on the bottom of
your screen right there. That'll take you to this
Google spreadsheet, which includes all the add-ons
I'm using. Any relevant profiles for them. You've
got the weak aura links as well. Very recently, I
started adding these GIFs too, just so you can get
a bit of a preview as to what they're all about.
Perhaps if you're on the fence, you're curious,
you're not too sure what the benefit of them are,
you can get a very quick and easy glimpse as to
what it's all about. So, yeah, tinyurl.com/skimmy.
Check it out and let me know how you're
going. Then, lastly, we have macros, which,
honestly speaking, are just as important, I'd
say, as your weak auras and add-ons because
they can combine multiple button presses into
one. They can just smooth out the gameplay
and just act as a nice quality of life change. So,
in the top left corner, you'll see my CDs button,
and this will just activate everything at
once, which is berserking, PI if talented,
use 10 as your engineering gloves, and then use 13
and 14 would be your trinkets. This works wonders
at the moment, right, because we're running double
passive trinkets. So, everything activates at
once, and there's no cooldown to contend with
Shadow Fiend. This one here, rather simple at
first because it just casts Shadow Fiend and
makes sure that the pet is attacking. But it
also does what I have added into basically every
other spell like mind blast, all my dots, as well
as Shadow Word: Death to the right. On first
pass, it will say, are you targeting an enemy,
and if none exists, then it's going to look to
make sure that you are, and if the target you're
currently attacking is now dead and you can't
harm it anymore, then it's going to run this
all again and look to try and find something new.
This is really handy, especially for things like
Shadow Word: Death, where you've got a bunch of
small adds constantly spawning, and you're trying
to snipe them for Twist of Fate procs as well as
shadow orbs. You're like, "Oh, I got to quickly
get in there, man. Like, what's happening?" And
then you spamming this button. It's going to
get it done for you, and you're going to thank
me in the comments in a later video. Later on,
you got Shadow Word: Death, and look, I love this
button. My Shadow Word: Death button. This says,
"Alright, what level 90 you taking? I'll update
a tooltip based on that." You never have to keep
dragging and dropping from your talents onto your
action bars. Then you got dispersion. This one,
yeah, you first cast, it's going to make sure the
buff's active. You cast it again, it's going to
cancel. Very similar to what you would have seen
with bubbles or BoPs for paladins. Then, lastly,
feather. Another reason why this is just the
goat is because you can remove the targeting
reticle completely and just cast this at your
own feet. That way, you've always got that Hot
Wheels energy just to blast around the map and
laugh at everybody else now being a wheelchair
in this expansion. So, those are the macros I
run. One thing, if you want to be super sweaty,
I saw this discussed in a Shadow Priest
Discord the other day, and I know there's
some weak auras out there that can do it for
you, those little talent calculators, but it's
been found that you can actually type this command
out, and it will switch the talent for you without
using a tome. Now, this is kind of insane because
you can now, on your second action bar row,
just quickly toggle between bosses or trash packs
and have no downtime, no click confirmation, just
switch between any talent choice at your leisure.
Be a good raider, be a good contributor, and look,
I use this all the time, quite honestly, when I'm
switching out for PvP, for open-world dailies,
into dungeons, into raids. It's really crazy. I'm
curious to see if Blizzard will change this or if
they'll let this one fly. Because as it stands,
this is a nice little quality of life buff as
well. But that about wraps it up for my guide. Let
me know what you thought in the comments section.
Any questions, anything I didn't cover, anything
you want to discuss about. Obviously, when the
new raid in Terrace comes out, we'll discuss
that one as well, and we'll make a part two.